<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Installing HCatalog</title>
  </header>
  <body>

  <section>
    <title>Server Installation</title>

    <p><strong>Prerequisites</strong></p>
    <ul>
        <li>Machine on which the server can be installed - this should have
        access to the hadoop cluster in question, and be accessible from
        the machines you launch jobs from</li>
        <li>MySQL db</li>
        <li>Hadoop cluster</li>
        <li>Unix user that the server will run as, and an associated kerberos
        service principal and keytabs.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Throughout these instructions when you see a word in <em>italics</em> it
    indicates a place where you should replace the word with a locally 
    appropriate value such as a hostname or password.</p>

    <p><strong>Database Setup</strong></p>

    <p>Select a machine to install the database on.  This need not be the same
    machine as the Thrift server, which we will set up later.  For large
    clusters we recommend that they not be the same machine.  For the 
    purposes of these instructions we will refer to this machine as
    <em>hcatdb.acme.com</em></p>

    <p>Install MySQL server on <em>hcatdb.acme.com</em>.  You can obtain
    packages for MySQL from <a href="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/">MySQL's
    download site</a>.  We have developed and tested with versions 5.1.46
    and 5.1.48.  We suggest you use these versions or later.
    Once you have MySQL up and running, use the <code>mysql</code> command line
    tool to add the <code>hive</code> user and <code>hivemetastoredb</code>
    database.  You will need to pick a password for your <code>hive</code>
    user, and replace <em>dbpassword</em> in the following commands with it.</p>

    <p><code>mysql -u root</code></p>
    <p><code>mysql> CREATE USER 'hive'@'</code><em>hcatdb.acme.com</em><code>' IDENTIFIED BY '</code><em>dbpassword</em><code>';</code></p>
    <p><code>mysql> CREATE DATABASE hivemetastoredb DEFAULT CHARACTER SET latin1 DEFAULT COLLATE latin1_swedish_ci;</code></p>
    <p><code>mysql> GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON hivemetastoredb.* TO 'hive'@'</code><em>hcatdb.acme.com</em><code>' WITH GRANT OPTION;</code></p>
    <p><code>mysql> flush privileges;</code></p>
    <p><code>mysql> quit;</code></p>

    <p>In a temporary directory, untar the HCatalog artifact</p>

    <p><code>tar xzf hcatalog-</code><em>version</em><code>.tar.gz</code></p>

    <p>Use the database installation script found in the package to create the
    database</p>
    <p><code>mysql -u hive -D hivemetastoredb -h</code><em>hcatdb.acme.com</em><code> -p &lt; share/hcatalog/hive/external/metastore/scripts/upgrade/mysql/hive-schema-0.7.0.mysql.sql</code></p>

    <p><strong>Thrift Server Setup</strong></p>

    <p>Select a machine to install your Thrift server on.  For smaller and test
    installations this can be the same machine as the database.  For the
    purposes of these instructions we will refer to this machine as
    <em>hcatsvr.acme.com</em>.</p>

    <p>Install the MySQL Java connector libraries on <em>hcatsvr.acme.com</em>.
    You can obtain these from
    <a href="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/connector/j/5.1.html">MySQL's
    download site</a>.</p>

    <p>Select a user to run the Thrift server as.  This user should not be a
    human user, and must be able to act as a proxy for other users.  We suggest
    the name "hcat" for the user.  Throughout the rest of this documentation 
    we will refer to this user as "hcat".  If necessary, add the user to 
    <em>hcatsvr.acme.com</em>.</p>

    <p>Select a <em>root</em> directory for your installation of HCatalog.  This 
    directory must be owned by the hcat user.  We recommend
    <code>/usr/local/hcat</code>.  If necessary, create the directory.</p>

    <p>Download the HCatalog release into a temporary directory, and untar
    it.  Then change directories into the new distribution and run the HCatalog
    server installation script.  You will need to know the directory you chose
    as <em>root</em> and the
    directory you installed the MySQL Java connector libraries into (referred
    to in the command below as <em>dbroot</em>).  You will also need your
    <em>hadoop_home</em>, the directory where you have Hadoop installed, and 
    the port number you wish HCatalog to operate on which you will use to set
    <em>portnum</em>.</p>

    <p><code>tar zxf hcatalog-</code><em>version</em><code>.tar.gz
    cd hcatalog-</code><em>version</em></p>
    <p><code>share/hcatalog/scripts/hcat_server_install.sh -r </code><em>root</em><code> -d </code><em>dbroot</em><code> -h </code><em>hadoop_home</em><code> -p </code><em>portnum</em></p>

    <p>Now you need to edit your <em>root</em><code>/etc/hcatalog/hive-site.xml</code> file.
    Open this file in your favorite text editor.  The following table shows the
    values you need to configure.</p>

    <table>
        <tr>
            <th>Parameter</th>
            <th>Value to Set it to</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>javax.jdo.option.ConnectionURL</td>
            <td>In the JDBC connection string, change DBHOSTNAME to the name 
            of the machine you put the MySQL server on.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>javax.jdo.option.ConnectionPassword</td>
            <td><em>dbpassword</em> value you used in setting up the MySQL server
            above</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.warehouse.dir</td>
            <td>The directory you want to use for the default database in your
            installation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.uris</td>
            <td>You need to set the hostname to your Thrift
            server.  Replace <em>SVRHOST</em> with the name of the
            machine you are installing the Thrift server on.  You can also
            change the port the Thrift server runs on by changing the default
            value of 3306.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.sasl.enabled</td>
            <td>Set to true by default.  Set to false if you do not wish to
            secure the thrift interface.  This can be convenient for testing.
            We do not recommend turning this off in production.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.kerberos.keytab.file</td>
            <td>The path to the Kerberos keytab file containg the metastore
            thrift server's service principal.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.kerberos.principal</td>
            <td>The service principal for the metastore thrift server.  You can
            reference your host as _HOST and it will be replaced with your
            actual hostname</td>
        </tr>
    </table>

    <p>You can now procede to starting the server.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting the Server</title>
            
    <p>Start the HCatalog server by switching directories to
    <em>root</em> and invoking the start script
    <code>share/hcatalog/scripts/hcat_server_start.sh</code></p>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>

    <p>Server activity logs and gc logs are located in
    <em>root</em><code>/var/log/hcat_server</code>.  Logging configuration is located at
    <em>root</em><code>/conf/log4j.properties</code>.  Server logging uses
    <code>DailyRollingFileAppender</code> by default. It will generate a new
    file per day and does not expire old log files automatically.</p>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Stopping the Server</title>

    <p>To stop the HCatalog server, change directories to the <em>root</em>
    directory and invoke the stop script
    <code>share/hcatalog/scripts/hcat_server_stop.sh</code></p>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Client Install</title>

    <p>Select a <em>root</em> directory for your installation of HCatalog client.
    We recommend <code>/usr/local/hcat</code>.  If necessary, create the directory.</p>

    <p>Download the HCatalog release into a temporary directory, and untar
    it.</p>

    <p><code>tar zxf hcatalog-</code><em>version</em><code>.tar.gz</code></p>

    <p>Now you need to edit your <em>root</em><code>/etc/hcatalog/hive-site.xml</code> file.
    Open this file in your favorite text editor.  The following table shows the
    values you need to configure.   These values should match the values set on
    the HCatalog server.  Do <strong>NOT</strong> copy the configuration file
    from your server installation as that contains the password to your
    database, which you should not distribute to your clients.</p>

    <table>
        <tr>
            <th>Parameter</th>
            <th>Value to Set it to</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.warehouse.dir</td>
            <td>The directory you want to use for the default database in your
            installation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>hive.metastore.uris</td>
            <td>You need to set the hostname wish your Thrift
            server to use by replacing <em>SVRHOST</em> with the name of the
            machine you are installing the Thrift server on.  You can also
            change the port the Thrift server runs on by changing the default
            value of 3306.</td>
        </tr>
    </table>

    <p>The HCatalog command line interface (CLI) can now be invoked as
    <em>root</em><code>/bin/hcat</code>.</p>

  </section>

  </body>
</document>
